Hello friends, welcome again. So we will
talk about a lot of quality interview
questions like which are asked in top
product based companies mostly right. So
let's get started without any delay. Now
I have this document.
Now for example let's start with the
question number one. So to practice on
my local let me create a database and I
will create a new database create
database let's say uh interview
questions interview
questions
okay
and now I will just use this use
interview
questions so to connect to this so that
whatever I do for this week I will be
doing under this particular database.
I hope this makes sense. Okay.
Fine. So let's see the question number
one. So let's see the question number
one. It says write a SQL query to
generate the following output by
comparing two tables. That means two
tables are given to us source and
target. Right? Now we have to compare
those two and we have to detect records
that are in source but not in target
right and label them as new in source
right that means something which is
there in source table but not in target
table and then same way we have to
detect something which is in target
table but not in source table and detect
records which are matching right but
have different names and that we have to
label as mismatch. So very I mean I
would say this is bit something between
easy and medium if I have to categorize
this problem
now I mean directly let's see the data
sets and you will understand so we
understand the source okay uh when I
copy here it is coming like this anyways
so source table let's say it is like
this ID name 1 A 2 B 3 C 4 D like that
and target is let's say 1 A 2 B 4X 5 A.
Now in this if you see if let's say what
do you think that is extra in source. So
out of 1 2 3 4 what is not there in
target right three is not there. So
three is new in source right and now
when you talk about new in target what
is there new five because five is not
there here right? So new in source is
three and new in target is five. That's
what it is. And mismatch is what is
matching let's say 1 A 1 A. So one is
both the places A only talking about two
here it is B here also it is B. Fine.
And talking about four you see here it
is D and here it is X. So there is a
mismatch. So four should be mismatch. So
the output that we want something like
the output that we want is
if you see three comma new in source
right uh whatever way we have to print
new in source
right
I mean we will see what capital letters
or whatever and five is new in target,
right? And what was the other one? Four
was a mismatch. Four was a mismatch.
This is the kind of result that we want
to print. So what I will do is I have
create table statements for this. So I
will create a source table, right? And a
target table and insert these values the
way it was shown, right? So let me take
all of this very quickly
and go here and run this. Done.
Right. So I have a source table and a
target table. Select
star from source.
Right. Just to show you if the table is
created.
So you can see this. And I will say
select star from target.
Target target.
Okay. So you can see we will have this
source and this target. Very easy to
analyze. Now
what we have to do here? What do we have
to do here? Very simple thing.
What we can do is see we can do a join
between the two tables right so we will
join the two tables the moment you have
two tables you understand that it it is
more like a join problem mostly right
because they want you to play with two
tables now let's say if I do let's say
my source table is the left one and
target table is the right one right and
if I let's Say do a left join between
these two. So source is on the left,
target is on the right. Let's say if I
do a left outer join
then what do you expect? What do what do
you think that left outer join do? Left
outer join says give me all the records
from the left table and even if there is
not a match on the right but give me all
the records from left and right side you
can show null. Right?
So now if you do a left outer join and
you see that okay uh on the right side
we are getting null right where where
let's say let's say you have source s
and target t and you are doing let's say
source s left outer join
right left join target t let's say this
is how you are writing your query
Now after that you apply a
join clause let's say you say on on what
condition right what was the condition
so if you see here id right s do id
equal to t dot id
s do id equal to t dot id right so
that's how we are joining the table so I
will say select
and I will just leave it
from
right so let's follow our pattern
whatever we follow so for explanation I
just started from middle but let's say
select from table name right join this
on this is a condition based on which we
are joining the two tables
right just have a look now if here here
let's say the right table has null.
Let's say if I say t do id
is null. What does that mean? What does
that mean? That right table does not
have the matching record. That that
means it is something new in the source.
It is new in the source. Right? I hope
you would agree with that. This is
something which is new in the source.
Have a look.
So I will just say
s do id that means it's there in source
but not in target because we are
filtering out the where target record is
not there right
okay and uh apart from that what comment
we have to put we have to say new in
source
right and it has to be I mean the column
name should should be comment right so
this is what it will give me so I mean
if I run this query it should give me
new in source
let me just run this
okay you see three is new in source
which is correct same way now now same
way if we slightly change it that
instead of left join let me make it a
right join
a right join let's say
and uh same condition and instead of t
dot id I say s do ID that means we are
saying give me all the records from
target right table right even though
there is a match on the left or not no
worries but give me all the records from
the right one and I'm saying left table
has null that means I'm saying record is
there in right but not in left and this
is new in target
new in target.
I hope this would make sense. And if I
run this,
you see five is new in target. We are
getting this correct. So I will just
take this query and I can do a union
here. I can do a union all. Should I do
union or union all? Think of it.
I mean you might say okay union if there
are duplicates it can remove but it's a
costly operation because it will check
whether duplicates are there or not
right but in this case you know there
cannot be any duplicates right so why do
we want union rather we can just say
union all which is a no-brainer for the
system and will be performant
right
so now
this aspect is done that new in source
new in target the third aspect what it
Third aspect what it is that okay when
they are matching but there is a
mismatch that means ids are matching
when we do inner join let's say it
matches but there is a mismatch name is
different so I can write one more union
all
union all and I can say so let me just
copy this and we will change it slightly
okay uh so So I will just say you can
just have a look here
source s and instead of left join I can
do a inner join now because I'm talking
only about the matching ones right I put
take in small only that's fine so it
says inner join target t so these are
the matching records I will get now
where condition what I have to put where
s dot name not equal to t dot name
that's what is a mismatch right ids are
matching but name is not matching I hope
this is clear and here what I will say s
do ID and this is mismatch
mismatch as comment
now if I run this query hopefully this
should run
let me just see that
So you can see three new in source new
in target. Let me see why the last one
is not printed. Uh so idly I was
expecting four to be printed right.
Oh sorry I have given this right. Uh
semicolon here. This should not be
given. I mean it is running the only
that part right. So now if you see this
gives me mismatch. So basically I
divided this problem into three parts.
Right. So this first part what it is
doing uh will find new in source. Right.
The second part what it will do will
find new in target. And the third part
what it will do
will find the mismatch.
Now new in source is something source is
left table. Target is the right table.
Now
something which is there extra in source
that is new in source. So that means you
do a left outer join and there should be
null on the right side. Now on the other
hand if you have to see new in target
that means let's say source is left
table target is the right one. It is
there in target but not in source. So
you do a right outer join and it should
be null in the left table. Right? And
mismatch means matching records but name
is not matching. Right? So that means
inner join and then you have this class.
So this is what I have done. Now I mean
we SQL query can be written in many
ways. Right? Now we could have combined
two of the things right? That means this
mismatch we could have combined with any
of this. I mean either this one or this
one. How to combine that? Right? I mean
even this is good. I mean a more
readable query but we could do a
variation of this. Let me just copy. Let
me just copy this
and show you that how I can let's say
merge this particular part the mismatch
part with let's say the first one itself
so that there are not two union alls
that we have to use right so what I will
do I will just remove this part and see
if I can merge somehow that part with
this one right so what I will do now is
let's say I will Say select S dot ID new
in sources comment from sources left
joint target T on this where T dot ID is
null here I will have the other
condition also or
S dotname not equal to T dot name
right that means whatever condition we
were having there here also we are
having that or condition or means it
will increase some records to us let's
say earlier we were getting just an
example five records. Now the moment we
are broadening our condition that means
we will get more records. Right? Now
when you are doing a left join it
automatically gives you the results of
inner join also plus it gives you some
extra. What is that extra? Something
which is there in left table but not in
right table. Inner join plus something
right table. Right? So that means
whatever we were doing in the third
query which with inner join we could do
here also now right.
So what we can do is uh here I can say
instead of this because now comment can
be of two types new insource if this
condition matches or if this condition
matches it will be mismatch. So what I
will do now is I will have a case
statement. So when we have to check
right then we have to do a case
statement right. So what I can do case
let's say when when
t dot id is null when t dot id is null
then what? Then
new insource new in source
right.
Okay.
And when
when
s dot name s dotname not equal to t dot
name right then
then mismatch.
As simple as that. And then we have to
end it case. So we end this. And now we
give some alias name to this column.
What name we want to give? As uh
comment, right?
So now you can see earlier there was no
case statement because only single new
insource was coming. But now based on
condition we are determining whether it
is new in source or mismatch. That's
where we have given a case statement.
And we have two when clauses to this.
Right? So this should give me the same
result as we were getting earlier.
Let's see.
Let us see that.
And you can check this out. Right? So
this is equivalent to my previous query.
So what I have done is this part I have
merged to this part. And just to check
the condition here I am using a case
statement right you can see this
but I if you personally ask me I would
prefer this one even though number of
lines are little more but this is more
readable and it's like more modular that
I this particular section will find new
insource this will find new in target
this will find the mismatch right I mean
so you you have to see that it's like
not just the number of lines of code
which matters but readability also
matters. Now if I have to someone has
written a query and I have to go through
the logic I will feel this one is easy
for me to interpret the first one right
because all the parts are separate
but here we mixed the first and third
part and the logic became slightly
complicated using a case statement.
I hope this would make sense to you
right
and remember one thing very very
important wherever you are sure that
there are no duplicates or something use
union all because the moment you use
union system do not know that duplicates
are not there it will still do the hard
work to think that oh if there are
duplicates I will remove them right so
in such cases if you are aware as a
programmer that duplicates are not there
then use union all rather than union
because it will be more performant. So
with this we are done with our
uh solution one for the question number
one and I hope you would have enjoyed
the session and keep watching this uh
series. Thank you.